Preliminary Inventory of the Japanese modern history manuscript collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Japanese modern history manuscript collection
circa 1868-1989
2004C32
Hoover Institution Archives
92 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 5 oversize folders (38.4 linear feet)
Manuscripts, ephemeral printed matter, and maps, relating to various aspects of Japanese history, including Nagano prefecture local government during the Meiji period; the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-1895; pre-World War II domestic affairs; the post-World War II American occupation; the International Military Tribunal for the Far East; adoption of a constitution; political conditions; elections; agriculture; communism; labor; public safety issues; Ryukyu issues; and the U.S.-Japan Security Treaty. Collected by the Hoover Institution East Asia Library.
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace. East Asia Library.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Scope and Content Note
Manuscripts, ephemeral printed matter, and maps, relating to various aspects of Japanese history, including Nagano prefecture local government during the Meiji period; the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-1895; pre-World War II domestic affairs; the post-World War II American occupation; the International Military Tribunal for the Far East; adoption of a constitution; political conditions; elections; agriculture; communism; labor; public safety issues; Ryukyu issues; and the U.S.-Japan Security Treaty. Collected by the Hoover Institution East Asia Library.
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace. East Asian Collection.; Agriculture--Japan.; Chinese-Japanese War, 1894-1895.; Communism--Japan.; Elections--Japan.; Japan--Economic conditions.; Japan--Foreign relations.; Japan--History--20th century.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Japan--Politics and government--20th century.; Japan--Social conditions.; Labor movement--Japan.; War crime trials--Japan.
- Japanese language inventory for boxes 1-82
  Other Finding Aids note
  Japanese Modern History Manuscript Collection Inventory (In Japanese)
- Araki Sadao (1877-1966) collection (Boxes 1-9)
- Irie Toshio (1901-1972) collection (Box 10)
- Shinoda Jisaku (1879-1946) collection (Boxes 11-21)
- Hamada Tokkai (1899-1958) collection (Boxes 22-26)
- Hiranuma Kiichiro (1867-1952) collection (Boxes 27-28, 91-92)
- Yano Toyotaro collection (Boxes 29-48)
- Miscellaneous items on pre-World War II domestic affairs (Boxes 49-54)
- Miscellaneous items on pre-World War II and immediately after the war (Boxes 55-57)
- Issues of post-World War II farmers (Box 58)
- Materials about Nihon Yusen (Box 59)
- Journals of local assembly meetings in Nagano Prefecture, Meiji Period (1868-1912) (Box 60)
- Paul Goforth collection (Box 61)
- Newspaper items on Sino-Japanese War, 1894-1895 (Box 62)
- Issues of post-World War II constitution (Box 63)
- International Military Tribunal for the Far East (Boxes 64-67)
- Issues regarding Ryukyu (Box 68)
- Post-World War II communist movement (Boxes 69-71)
- Post-World War II labor movement (Box 72)
- Post-World War II public safety issues (Box 73)
- Leaflets regarding U.S.-Japan Security Treaty (Box 74)
- Post-World War II elections in Japan (Box 75)
- Miscellaneous items on post-World War II Japan (Boxes 76-77)
- Maps (Map case case)
  Scope and Contents note
  5 oversize folders formerly housed in Boxes 78-82.
- Incremental materials (Boxes 83-95)
- Incremental materials acquired in 2014 (Boxes 96-98)
  Memoranda, minutes of meetings, writings, memoirs, statistics, and interviews relating to Chiang Kai-shek's secret Japanese military advisers (Baituan) in the 1950s and the 1960s.